Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is ק"ד *kuf daled*,
104, and we picked up at the very bottom of ק"ג *kuf
gimmel*, עמוד ב' bet, *amud bet*, 103b, and we were in the
middle of the issue about if somebody writes שם shem, *shem*, שי"ן
מ"ם shin mem *shin-mem*, from the middle of writing the name שמעון
*Shimon*, then since that was part of what one was doing, one
is חייב chayav *chayav*. And to remind everybody the basic principle is
you need to write two letters, but apparently the two letters have
to be a name from
his own or a word. There was even a question whether two
of the same letter, even if it is a word, which was
the strange reason why the דף *daf* demands that they be different
letters. Anyway, that's but we're talking about two letters that make a
word. So if you write שם *shem* from the word שמעון *Shimon*,
even though it was part of what you were intending, since that
is a word, you're חייב chayav *chayav*. And the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s
question is, but when you read שם *shem* and you were intending
to write שמעון *Shimon*, the מ"ם mem, *mem* was an open מ"ם
mem *mem*, and the word שם *shem* is a closed מ"ם Mem
*mem*. So how's it considered to be that you actually wrote a
full word? So the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s answer is, first tries to
say, well, maybe that would count, maybe an open מ"ם *mem* counts
as a closed מ"ם *mem*. Counts in what context? In what הלכה
halacha. *halacha* context? In writing a ספר תורה sefer Torah? *sefer torah*,
maybe if you wrote an open מ"ם *mem* instead of a closed
מ"ם *mem*, it's valid. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says that can't
be, it quotes a very long ברייתא *braita* that speaks about not
confusing letters, writing letters similarly as a דל"ת Dalet *dalet* like a
רי"ש *reish*, a כ"ף *chaf* like a בי"ת Beis *bet*, and also
not writing an open מ"ם *mem* like a closed מ"ם *mem* or
vice-versa. So you see that it's not valid. So why when you
wrote שי"ן מ"ם *shin-mem* with an open מ"ם *mem* was it considered
like you wrote a full word? So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* now
comes to answer this and it says four lines from the bottom
on ק"ג *kuf gimmel* עמוד ב' bet *amud bet*, it says, הוא
He-vav-aleph, דאמר כי האי תנא *Hu de-amar ki hai tanna*, he says,
the author of our משנה Mishnah *mishna* says like the following תנא
*tanna*, דתניא *de-tanya*, which we turn in the ברייתא *braita*, beginning of
the third line from the bottom, רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר *Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira omer*, נאמר בשני ונסכיהם *ne'emar bi-shnei ve-niskhei-hem*, בששי ונסכיה
*be-shishi ve-niskhe-ha*, בשביעי כמשפטם *bi-shevi'i ke-mishpatam* ונסכיהם *ve-niskei-hem*. Thank you. This is
how we know a רמז *remez* to the idea that there's ניסוך
המים *nisuch hamayim*, you do the libations of water over סוכות *sukkot*.
So there's different opinions in the גמרא Gemara, *gemara* in סוכה *sukka*
where we know this idea from. Anyway, רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says
you get it because all of the various days of סוכות *sukkot*
where it mentions the קרבנות *korbanot*, it says ונסכו *ve-nisko*, but in
three places it says something slightly different.
That on the second day it says ונסכיהם *ve-niskei-hem*, so the מ"ם
*mem* is extra. On the sixth day it
says ונסכיה *ve-niskhe-ha*, so the
יו"ד *yud* is extra. And on the seventh day it says כמשפטם
*ke-mishpatam* instead of כמשפט *ke-mishpat*, so the מ"ם *mem* is extra. מ"ם
יו"ד מ"ם *mem-yud-mem*, מים mayim, *Mayim*. מכאן רמז לניסוך המים מן התורה
*Mi-kan remez le-nisuch hamayim min ha-Torah*. So that's how you know that
on סוכות *sukkot* you do ניסוך המים *nisuch hamayim*, you pour the
water in the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. It's a Bible source! There
you go. Now, don't worry, we'll get to that. Now, the problem
is that the first מ"ם *mem* in ונסכיהם *ve-niskei-hem* is a מ"ם
סופית *mem sofit*. So you see that if you can use it
to make a דרשה drasha *drasha*, a מ"ם סופית *mem sofit* to
count as an open מ"ם *mem*, it shows that somehow halakhically that
also counts, you know, that we would see them as interchangeable. It's
a little bit question if they would even go so far to
think that that would even be valid in a ספר תורה sefer
Torah *sefer torah*, but anyway that's the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s argument. So
the גמרא Gemara, *gemara* says, ומידי פתוח ועשאו סתום כשר kosher. *u-midipatuach
ve-asao satum kasher*, if what was open you made closed it's כשר
kasher. *kasher*, because here a סתום *satum* מ"ם *mem* stands in for
an open מ"ם *mem*. If that's true, סתום נמי *satum nami*, so
the same would be in the reverse. ומידי פתוח ועשאו סתום כשר,
kasher. סתום נמי, ומה סתום ועשאו פתוח כשר kasher,
*u-ma satum ve-asao patuach kasher*, if it was something that was closed
that should have been closed and you made it open, it's כשר
*kasher*. So if you wrote שם *shem* and the מ"ם *mem* was
open, it counts as if it was a closed מ"ם *mem*. It's
interesting by the way that the גמרא Gemara *gemara* doesn't discuss, you
know, maybe should we go by how common people write, even if
it doesn't have halakhic significance to count as equivalent. Maybe it couldn't
go by that, maybe you know in the common writing it was
written always the right way. So but it is an interesting question
when you're writing like in Hebrew and that and the writing in
Hebrew has halakhic standards that apply elsewhere, like writing ספרי תורה *sifrei
torah*, to what degree when you're writing for like laws of שבת
Shabbos. *shabbos* would you look at standard הלכות *halachos* of how those
are written or would you look at like the way common people
write. For example, it's obvious that you don't have to write the
letter exactly in the way that makes it a כשר *kasher* writing
for a ספר תורה sefer Torah, *sefer torah* in order to be
חייב chayav *chayav* for שבת Shabbos. *shabbos*. So it is interest—right, let's
say you didn't put the little crowns on top of the letter
or you didn't do some of those tiny little details. So it
is interesting here anyway that the גמרא Gemara, *gemara* is looking at
those laws to determine why an open מ"ם *mem* should count as
a closed מ"ם *mem*.
What was the ancient script?
Did they have the
open—so that's actually an interesting point. The ancient Hebrew script in terms
of—the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s actually going to get to that in one
minute. So let's just hold off for that for one second. So
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says like this, מי דמי *mi dami*? One
minute, you can't compare, even if you wanted to base yourself on
that דרשה drasha *drasha* of מים mayim. *Mayim*. פתוח ועשאו סתום *patuach
ve-asao satum*, if it should have been open and you made it
closed like that דרשה drasha *drasha* of מים mayim, *Mayim*, עילויי קמעלי
*iluye kama'ali*.
You're raising up the letter. It's better to be a closed letter.
Somehow that's considered a higher status of the letter. Very strange. You
would think a normal letter is the shape it has in the
middle. We'll see why that is in a minute. Because of the
following: דאמר רב חסדא *de'amar Rav Chisda*, רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says:
מם וסמך שבלוחות Mem ve'Samekh she'be'luchos, בנס היו עומדים *Mem v'Samech shebaluchos
b'nes hayu omdim*. So first we're going to talk about—the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to assert, just to tell you what's coming, that
the middle letters were introduced later. Originally in the script, you only
had the closed letters. The middle letters were introduced, you know, that
there would be a difference, the non-סופיות *sofiot*, the open letters—the open
מם *mem*, for example, or the open נון *nun*, or whatever—the idea
that it was different in the middle was later. Originally it always
looked like it looks now at the end. That's going to be
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s argument. And therefore, if you made something that
should have been opened closed, you're really just reverting it to its
original form. And therefore, it's okay. So make something open closed, that's
okay. But to make something that should be closed open, that's not
good. That's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s argument. Now how are we going
to argue that those middle versions of the letters came later? Because
we have a teaching of רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* that the מם
*mem* and סמך Samekh, *samech* in the לוחות luchos *Luchos* stood in
a miracle. What does that mean? The מם סופית *mem sofit* and
the סמך *samech*, if you were to carve something all the way
through, right, then you would have basically just a hole, because there
would be like the middle section, right, of a מם *mem*, right?
There's nothing to hold it in place. And the same with a
סמך *samech*. If you imagine that the לוחות luchos? *Luchos* were carved
from one side to the other side, so how did the מם
*mem* and the סמך *samech* exist if it was carved all the
way through? It was a miracle—that middle block, you know, that allowed
it to look like a מם *mem* or סמך *samech*, that was
suspended in mid-air. That's מם וסמך שבלוחות בנס היו עומדים *Mem v'Samech
shebaluchos b'nes hayu omdim*. Interestingly,
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi. *Yerushalmi* says: עין שבלוחות בנס היו עומדי *Ayin shebaluchos
b'nes hayu omdei*. The עין *ayin*. Why? Because in ancient Hebrew script,
the עין *ayin*, like an eye, actually looks like a סמך *samech*.
Right. In ancient Hebrew, the עין *ayin* looks like a סמך *samech*.
So therefore, the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* assumes that the לוחות luchos? *Luchos* were
written in the ancient Hebrew script. Now, actually the Ten Commandments, what
they had it written in the ancient Hebrew? Okay. Anyway, so, so
it's actually interesting because in another גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, not here, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks this question about, you know, כתב אשורית *Ktav
Ashurit*, Assyriac script, and כתב עברית *Ktav Ivrit*, Hebrew script—Hebrew is the
ancient Hebrew script. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't want to accept
that our current script was, you know, introduced later, because then how
do you have a כשר ספר תורה sefer Torah, *kasher Sefer Torah*
by script that wasn't around at the time of משה Moshe, רבינו
*Moshe Rabbeinu*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually, in the בבלי Bavli
*Bavli* actually argues—this is in מגילה *Megillah*—that we started with the כתב
אשורית *Ktav Ashurit*, we then went to ancient Hebrew script, and then
we came back to כתב אשורית *Ktav Ashurit*, which is a little
hard to believe. So it is worth noting, and we're going to
say something along those lines here in a minute about a—another point.
So it is interesting to note though, the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* has no
problem with that. The ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* assumes the לוחות luchos *Luchos* were
written in ancient Hebrew script, and therefore says the עין *ayin* was
בנס *b'nes*, not the מם *mem* and סמך *samech*. Like a מם
*mem* and סמך *samech*? Yeah. Like an eye. I don't know. It
may be more pointed at the edges. You'll have to look at
those charts. I'm not sure what the סמך *samech* looked like. You
can look up on the charts of the ancient Hebrew script. I
thought I had one at home.
I'll bring it in.
Rat—yeah. No, that's not ancient Hebrew. Okay. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this—you'll look it up, it's very easy to find
on the internet—the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay. Anyway, so
that shows you that at the time of the לוחות *Luchos*, we
certainly had the end letters, because it says you had a מם
*mem* that was בנס *b'nes*. So it shows you had the end
letters at the time of the לוחות *Luchos*. Now how do you
know you didn't have the middle letters at the time of the
לוחות *Luchos*? So we'll—so we'll see that in a minute. אלא ela,
סתום ועשאו פתוח *Ella satum va'asao patuach*—it should have been closed and
you made it open—גרועי קא מגרע ליה *geruay kama gara lei*—you're making
it worse because open letters came later, like the open מם *mem*.
How do you know the open מם *mem* came later? דאמר רבי
ירמיה ואיתימא רבי חייא בר אבא *De'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah v'iseima Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba*, because רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah* says, some say רבי חייא
בר אבא *Rabbi Chiya bar Abba*: מנצפך *Manatzpach*, מם *Mem*, נון *Nun*,
צדי tzaddi *Tzadi*, פי *Pei*, כף *Chaf*, those are all letters that
are different in the middle than at the end, right? Everybody know
that? See that, right? Those are all the letters that are different
in the middle and the end. Those צופים אמרום *Tzofim amrum*. Those
were said by the prophets, meaning that there would be a different
כתב *ktav* for middle and end. Now by the way, it's a
little play on words: מן צופייך *min tzofayich*.
מנצפך *Manatzpach* means from your צופייך *tzofayich*, from your seers, from your—from
your prophets. Okay? So those—that idea was introduced by the prophets, that
there would be a different lettering for the—the middle and the end.
So since we've already asserted that by the time of the לוחות
*Luchos*, the end letters were there, because that was בנס היו עומדים
*b'nes hayu omdim*, what did the prophets introduce? The prophets must have
introduced the middle letter. Okay? So you got that? At the time
of the לוחות *Luchos*, you had the end letters, that was the
מם *mem* that was בנס *b'nes*. Prophets introduced two types, so what
type did they introduce? They introduced the middle ones. So the middle
is a later version. So if you write a middle like an
end letter, that's better, that's the original. But if you write a—an
end letter like a middle letter, that should not be acceptable. And
we're back to our question of שין *Shin* from שמעון *Shimon*. Okay?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says—so we still have our question—so the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* refuses to accept though that argument. ותסברה *Vetisbera*? Does
it really make sense to think that the prophets introduced a new—
orthography like a new writing of the letters? והכתיב, the verse says
אלה המצוות, eileh hamitzvos, these are the מצוות, mitzvos, שאין נביא רשאי
לחדש דבר מעתה, shein navi rishai lechadesh davar me'atah, that only the
מצוות mitzvos given from משה, Moshe, a later prophet cannot introduce new
מצוות mitzvos and somehow the גמרא Gemara understands that introducing a new
script is introducing new מצוות. mitzvos. Maybe because it just is a
general sort of conservatism approach about everything, you can't introduce anything new.
Maybe or maybe it's because of the sense, you know, about the
sort of the holiness of the letters and of the script, which
we'll sort of see a little bit about in a minute. Or
maybe because the script relates to the הלכה. halacha. How do you
have to write a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah How do you have
to write a, you know, a מזוזה mezuzah and תפילין? tefillin? So
if you're introducing new lettering, you're changing the מצוה. mitzvah. So therefore
it refuses to accept that the new letters were introduced in the
middle. So the גמרא Gemara. says, אלא מהוה הוה. ella mehavah havah.
Fine, there always were two forms of the letter. מדי לא הוו
ידעין. midei lo havu yadin. It wasn't always—it wasn't known which was
the middle, which was the end. Maybe they used them somewhat interchangeably.
There were two forms, but used interchangeably. האי באמצע תיבה והאי בסוף
תיבה. hai be-emtza teiva vehai besof teiva.
They didn't know which goes in the middle, which goes at the
end. ואתו צופים ותקנינהו. va'asu tzofim tikninu. Came the prophets and they
established certain ones in the middle, certain ones at the end. So
the גמרא Gemara doesn't like that. והא כתיב אלה המצוות שאין נביא
רשאי לחדש דבר מעתה. ve-ha ketiv eileh hamitzvos shein navi rishai lechadesh
davar me'atah. So what? You're still introducing something new. Now actually, not
necessarily in the sense that if it was acceptable both ways, if
they were interchangeable before and now we said it's a specific way,
you're not actually, you know, making something valid that was invalid. You're
introducing a new restriction. But maybe that's also the problem. Now you're
going to make me throw out a מזוזה, mezuzah, to bury a
מזוזה mezuzah that otherwise would have been כשר. So who are they
to, you know, to establish a new form of writing even if
it's more restrictive? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
רב חסדא, ella Rav Chisda, you must say שכחום וחזרו ויסדום. shichachum
vechazru veyisdum.
That okay, it always was this way that there were middle letters
and end letters,
but at—there was a period of time where they forgot, you know,
to make both types or they forgot which order they went or
they became sloppy and used them both ways. And then the prophets
came and they re-established it the old way, which ones were in
the middle, which ones were at the end. So this is similar
to the בבלי'ס Bavli's idea here that it's very conservative in terms
of this sense that not only do you not get new מצוות
mitzvos after משה, but you actually even like changes in the script
couldn't happen and even small changes, middle letters and end letters, or
making it more regular rather than more interchangeable. So anyway and therefore
it says that no, it always—the prophets did is they re-established it,
they were מחזיר עטרה ליושנה. machzir atara leyoshna. They reminded us what
the way it always used to be. Now how does that in
the end finish our argument? It finishes our argument because if it's
true that it always was a middle letter and an end letter
and we see for this דרשה derasha of מים, we could use
an end letter to represent a middle one, so then similarly if
you wrote the word שם, שין מם with an open מם, it
counts as writing a name because if an end can represent a
middle, a middle can represent an end. So it's a little funny,
ironically, because it was always fixed, therefore you can prove from one
way to the other that even if you're sloppy and do it
the other way, so even though for a ספר תורה it wouldn't
count and even though the normal way of writing—that's not normal—it's enough
recognized as representing the other way that it still counts. One does
wonder if according to this it would even count in a ספר
תורה, the one that's making the דרשה derasha מים. But at least
it counts enough for writing on שבת. Shabbos, And again the question,
as I said, is that do you mean to tell me that
if a, it's not, you know, if people never write this way
just because based on this דרשה derasha. of מים, but if normal
people never write that way, that still is enough of a standard
to make me חייב chayav. even if, you know, it's—in the way
we write and read it doesn't count. It's unclear, you know, again
how much we use these like halachic standard of writing in other
areas to be relevant for what constitutes writing on שבת. Shabbos. But
anyway that is a question. And I'll just mention to you although
we have said and we do פוסק pasken that writing for example
is in all languages, there is an opinion of the ראשונים Rishonim
based on a certain גמרא, Gemara which the גמרא Gemara doesn't say
but it's his way of reading something into the גמרא, Gemara that
actually against everything we're saying here that you're actually only חייב chayav
if you write Hebrew. You're not חייב chayav. if you write other
languages. So some doctors, you know, when they have to write things
on שבת, Shabbos. you know, you know, some people throw that in
as an extra leniency, try to write in a language other than
Hebrew, which isn't a problem if you're not an Israeli doctor. But
anyway,
but—but—but that does rest—get to the question of how much does the
sense of does it constitute writing go by sort of our societal
norms and conventions of writing or how much does it go by
some objective הלכה. halacha. If this is the way the מם is
supposed to look in ספר תורה, that counts here. So the question
of Hebrew and other languages touches on that a little bit as
well. Yes, Michael.
So is part of the reason why we're spending so much more
time on—on this because we don't פוסק pasken like רבי יוסי? Rabbi
Yosei? Because you know, he said just even if you do like
a שריטה, serita, then you're חייב. chayav. You know, so we reject
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei or we just don't know yet?
No, we haven't פוסק pasken yet. You are always assuming we're פוסק.
pasken. גמרא Gemara. almost never discusses הלכה. We're just analyzing the different
positions. All right, so anyway, so that's the—so that is the position
here, the גמרא, Gemara that these things were introduced—now I don't know.
I didn't check, but I do whether whether again whether archaeologically whether
we've discovered in terms of the script, this issue about whether they,
the end letters, whether they were, whether that was a later introduction
into the script or not or the middle letters, the difference between
middle and end. But I do know there clearly are differences in
writings you see that change over time get a little more conventional
or fixed. Like for example, you know in the Torah sometimes the
word hi, she, is spelled ה-ו-א, right, not ה-י-א. He-yod-aleph. So the
vav and the yod you know sometimes in the spelling... some people
say it's a קרי וכתיב, krei u'ksiv, it's not, sometimes that was
seen as interchangeable the vav and the yod in that type of
especially to represent I think a חיריק, chirek, you know yod. Anyway,
so there are these changes do get introduced and the בבלי sort
of is first recognizing maybe that came later, but then pushes back
and says no no no we can't we can't accept that there
were ever any changes in the script. Again as against the ירושלמי.
Okay, so now the גמרא continues. It says like this: גופא. Gufa.
אמר רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: מם וסמך שבלוחות בנס היו עומדין
Mem ve'Samekh she'be'luchos be'nes hayu omdim that they were suspended in mid-air,
it was a נס nes the מם and the סמך, because there
was nothing to hold the middle block.
ואמר רב חסדא: Ve'amar Rav Chisda: כתב שבלוחות נקרא מבפנים ונקרא מבחוץ.
Kesav she'be'luchos nikra mi-p'nim ve-nikra mi-bachutz. The writing on the לוחות can
it was read side frontwards and backwards, like you know when it
was front was facing you and when you're looking behind it because
it was carved all the way through. כגון: Kegon: נבוב בובן, Nevuv
Buban, if there
was the word נבוב Nevuv like נבוב לוחות Nevuv Luchot and you
were reading it from the back, it wouldn't read נבוב, Nevuv, it
would read בובן Buban because obviously you were, you know, reversed. You're
getting it reversed. Also the letters would be flipped also. It wouldn't
just be right to left, left to right different, right? It would
be actually... what... right, it would be... I'm trying to think... if
you... yeah,
it would be not only the words would be reversed in order,
but also each letter would be flipped. Okay,
אלקים. Elokim. סרו Saru ורס. Veras. So רהב בהר, Rahab Bahar, so
בהר רהב. Bahar Rahab. So anyway תוספות Tosafot says: what are we
doing using these examples, you know, these weren't words in the לוחות?
Why didn't he use words in the לוחות? I mean, so that's
that's interesting. I mean the word בהר be-har is there, you know,
in the story. נבוב Nevuv is there. סרו Saru סרו מהר מן
הדרך אשר צויתים. saru maher min ha-derech asher tzivisim. But why are
we actually putting... it's unclear. And also what's he saying that's different
than מם וסמך שבלוחות, which is saying it was carved all the
way through? It's not so clear. The מהרש"א Maharsha says what he's
trying to say is don't think part of the נס nes was
that when you looked on the other side, it read the exact
same way as front-wise. Like that would also be a נס. nes.
You look backwards and it read exactly the right way. No, no,
no, backwards it looked backwards. Okay, that's not so interesting. So the
מהרש"א Maharsha actually says well actually it's a lead-in to the next
discussion which is going to touch on this idea of sort of
like the mystical meaning of the letters. So to actually tell you
there was a reason it was read backwards, that there was a
hidden meaning in the backwards reading as well. That's how what he
wants to read into this. I mean obviously it's not what's being
stated but that's what he sort of sees it tying into something
that's maybe touches on a theme that's coming up.
Yeah, there's a hidden code. Like wasn't one of the Beatles' records
if you play it backwards it said John is dead or something?
Or was that Paul is dead? Which record was that?
Anyway, John Lennon.
The White Album. Okay, so anyway, so apparently according to the מהרש"א
Maharsha if you read the לוחות backwards there was a hidden code
there as well.
Like reading it backwards on the college radio station.
Okay, alright, so now the גמרא continues. אמרו ליה רבנן לרבי יהושע
בן לוי: Amru lei rabbanan le-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: so the rabbis
said to Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: אתו דרדקי האידנא Asu dardekei ha-idna
some schoolkids came today לבי מדרשא le-bei midrasha to the בית מדרש
beit medrash ואמרו מילי דאפילו ביומי יהושע בן נון לא איתמר כוותייהו,
ve-amru mili de-afilu b'yomei Yehoshua bin Nun lo ismar kevasaihu,
and they said words and things like this weren't even said from
the times of יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun. Now I'll mention
in a minute why it mentions יהושע בן נון. Yehoshua bin Nun.
But let's see what they said. אלף בית: Aleph-Beis: so basically it's
a whole דרשה derasha. on the אלף בית. Aleph-Beis. Okay, how to
like read words into the אלף בית. Aleph-Beis. אלף בית: Aleph-Beis: אלף
בינה, Alef Binah, learn wisdom. Okay, אלף בית, Aleph-Beis, בית for בינה,
Binah, אלף אלף, alef alef, learn. Learn wisdom. גימל דלת: Gimmel-Dalet: גמול
דלים. Gemol Dalim. So גימל Gimmel גמול, Gemol, דלת Dalet? דלים. Dalim.
You should you should you know give kindness to to poor people,
like גמילות חסד. gemilus chesed. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama now now you
notice by the way I should point out that in this דרשה
derashah here,
the Hebrew part is the original דרשה. derashah Inserted in it is
Aramaic which is later layer inserted into the גמרא and the גמרא
even gives like another another like you know elaborates even further on
this דרשה. So now the גמרא sort of is inserting into this.
מאי טעמא פשוטה כרעיה דגימל לגבי דלת? Mai ta'ama peshuta kar-ei de-Gimmel
legabei Dalet? Why is the leg of the גימל, Gimmel, right, the
thing that goes down at an angle, why is that pointed towards
the דלת? Dalet. So it says: שכן דרכו של גומל חסדים לרוץ
אחר דל. She'ken darko shel gomeil chasadim larutz achar dal. If you're
really a גומל חסד, gomeil chesed, you're not just סתם stam a
guy that gives צדקה. tzedakah. You're really גומל חסד gomeil chesed like
it's it comes with kindness and love and emotion and so on,
then you're going to be running after the poor person. So that's
why the leg of the גימל Gimmel is stuck out to run
after the דלת. Dalet ומאי טעמא פשוטה כרעיה דדלת לגבי גימל? U'mai
ta'ama peshuta kar-ei de-Dalet legabei Gimmel? Why is the leg of the
דלת I mean here the way it's printed it's like straight down,
you know, 90 degree angle. but really when you write it, it's
at a slight rightward angle. So why is the leg of the
ד dalet a little tilted towards the ג? gimmel? דלימצי ליה נפשיה?
Delimtzei leh nafshia? Because the עני ani isn't running, he wants to
make it a little bit, he doesn't want to run away too
fast from the guy who wants to give him the צדקה, tzedakah,
so he makes himself a little bit available. So he holds back
a little bit.
ומאי טעמא מהדר אפי דדלית מגימל? Umai ta'ama mahader apei de'dalet mi'gimmel?
So why is the ד dalet facing away from the ג, gimmel,
right, as it were, the head of the ד dalet is, he's
pointing away, if you see the top thing is like his head,
he's pointing away from the ג. gimmel. So
דליתי ליה בצינעא, Delitei leh be'tzina, so the person giving the money
to the עני, ani, the עני ani doesn't have to look at
him directly when he's receiving the money, which would be degrading or
embarrassing, and therefore it could be like you drop it in his,
you deposit it without him having to be shamed by looking by
looking directly at the person who is giving. כי היכי דלא ליכסוף
מיניה, Ki hechi de'lo lichsof mineh, he shouldn't be embarrassed. Okay, so
that's a very nice little דרשה on גמל דלת gimmel dalet as
גומל דלים gomel dalim and going even further into the exact shape
of the letters. ה ו, Hey vav, זה שמו של הקדוש ברוך
הוא, zeh shemo shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu, okay, that's half of God's
name, the ה ו. hey vav. ז ח ט י כ ל.
Zayin chet tet yud chaf lamed. ואם אתה עושה כן, Ve'im atah
oseh chen, so if you do this what will God do? הקדוש
ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu זן אותך, zan otcha, that's the ז,
zayin, God will sustain you וחונך אותך, ve'chonecha otcha, וחנך אותך, ve'channecha
otcha, will give you kindness, ומטיב לך, u'metiv lecha, that's the ט,
tet, give you goodness, ונותן לך ירושה, ve'noten lecha yerushah, an inheritance,
that's the י, yud, וקושר לך כתר ve'qosher lecha keter לעולם הבא,
le'olam haba, and the כ chaf is a crown ל lamed for
עולם הבא. olam haba. So if you learn Torah and give and
give צדקה tzedakah and are גומל חסד, gomel chesed, then God will
do all these things for you. Okay, now we get to the
מ. mem. So now we have remember, an open מ mem and
a closed מ, mem, which we've already established was ancient. So מם
פתוחה מם סתומה. mem petucha mem setuma. So what does that tell
you? מאמר פתוח מאמר סתום. Ma'amar patuach ma'amar satum. Words that are
open and words that are closed. רש"י Rashi says that
there's Torah that should be taught and then there's esoteric Torah, Torah
that should be hidden. That's the way רש"י Rashi reads it. So
you have to also be use, not everything should be spoken about.
נון כפופה נון פשוטה, Nun kefufah nun peshutah, a bent נ nun
and a straight נ. nun. So נאמן כפוף, ne'eman kafuf, a trustworthy
person, but נאמן ne'eman also means like a righteous person, should be
bowed down, ונאמן פשוט, ve'ne'eman pashut, and he should be straight up.
So what does that mean he should be bowed down and straight
up? So רש"י Rashi says he's bowed down in this world, he's
humble in this world, he's straight up in עולם הבא olam haba
he gets his reward. המהרש"א HaMaharsha says, which I also was thinking
that it connects to a גמרא like this that speaks about the
שופר shofar ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, that there's two opinions. One says
it should be bent and the other says it should be straight
up. Bent because you should like bend your stature, a sense of
humility and humbleness before God, and straight up, a sense of looking
up to God, reaching up to God. So there's a sense of
in your stature being bent, being humble, but your eyes and your
religious yearnings are straight up and are reaching towards God.
Nun pashutah is a nun sofit?
Yeah, נון פשוטה nun peshutah is straight, it's the נון סופית. nun
sofit.
And nun kafufah because the bottom is bent in a little?
Yeah, exactly. Yeah, bent because it bends in and פשוטה peshutah because
it's straight down. ס ע, Samech ayin, סמוך עניים, semoch aniyim,
support the poor people. So it's repeating an idea like the גמל
דלת. gimmel dalet. לשון אחר, Lashon acher, another version of this is
סימנים עשה בתורה, simanim aseh ba'Torah,
make for yourself signs in the Torah like mnemonics, ways to remember
your Torah. Okay, so going back to the אלף בית, alef beit,
the אלוף בינה, aluf binah, the learning Torah that we had mentioned
before.
וקנה, Uknei, and therefore you'll be able to acquire Torah. פה כפופה
פה פשוטה, Peh kefufah peh peshutah, a bent פ, peh, a middle
פ peh and a פ peh at the end which is more
straight, a straight leg. פה פתוח פה סתום. Peh patuach peh satum.
Same idea as the מ, mem, an open mouth, a closed mouth,
things you talk about, things you don't talk about. צדי כפופה צדי
פשוטה, Tzaddi kefufah tzaddi peshutah, a צדי tzaddi that is bent, a
middle צדי tzaddi. and an end צדי. צדיק כפוף צדיק פשוט. Tzaddik
kafuf tzaddik pashut. Same like we said by the נאמן. ne'eman. A
righteous person bent down, a righteous person straight up. So גמרא says
היינו נאמן כפוף נאמן פשוט, hainu ne'eman kafuf ne'eman pashut, we just
said that by the נ. nun. So הוסיף לך הכתוב כפיפה על
כפיפתו. Hosif lecha hakatuv kefifah al kefifato. To tell you that you
should take extra extra measures to bend down as a righteous person,
you really have to strive for greater humility. מכאן שנתנה תורה במנדוד
ראש. Mikan she'nitna Torah be'mandud rosh.
Here you see the Torah was given in like in the lowering
of the head, the bending of the head. המהרש"א HaMaharsha quotes another
famous דרשה which says like מאד מאד, me'od me'od, a line from
פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, הוי שפל רוח. hevei shefal ruach. You should
very much try to be like of lowly spirit. It's actually very
counter-Greek idea of, Greeks felt like being humble was שקר. sheker. You
should be proud of everything that you do, that's אמת. emet. That's
what the Greeks thought. So חז"ל Chazal were very emphasize the sense
of humility before God. So here they're saying that's why it's repeated.
Semoch aniyim is different than gimmel dalet?
Yeah, well that's true, but גמילות חסד gemilut chesed is different than
צדקה. tzedakah. So it's not exactly the same. So the גמרא says
and that- It might be also why the גמרא gave another explanation.
Of ק, kuf, the ק kuf is קדוש, kadosh, holy, is God.
ר reish is רשע. rasha. Now we're introducing—all that was if you
were the righteous, but now when we introduce somebody, somebody could be
a רשע. rasha. So now you have God right next to the
רשע. rasha. So מאי טעמא מהדר אפיה דקוף מרשע? mai ta'ama mahadar
apei de-kuf mei-reisha? Why is the ק kuf not facing the ר?
reish? Meaning the way that the ר reish is, you know, facing
away from the ק, kuf, like the ד dalet was facing away
from the ג? gimel? So אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar Hakadosh Baruch
Hu, אין אני יכול להסתכל ברשע, ein ani yakhol lehistakel barasha, I
can't look at the רשע, rasha, let him turn away from me.
ומאי טעמא מהדר תגיה דקוף לגבי ריש? u-mai ta'ama mahadar tagei de-kuf
legabei reish?
So why is the little tag, the little crown, like on the
type of a ק kuf you make a little like a little
on the top of the ק kuf you make like a little
stick with a with a ball on top, a little a little
crown, and that leans towards the ר? reish? Why is that? So
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, אם חוזר בו, im
chozer bo, if he does תשובה, teshuvah, אני קושר לו כתר כמותי,
ani kosher lo keter kemoti,
I'll give him a crown like I have on my head. Okay,
so God even though God is not looking at the רשע, rasha,
in a way he's reaching out to the רשע. rasha. ומה טעמא
כרעיה דקוף תלויה? u-mai ta'ama kura de-kuf tluyah?
Why is the leg of the ק, kuf, why is it suspended?
Right, the leg and sometimes especially you'll see this in some manuscripts,
right, the סופר sofer is like, you know, it's easier, he just
writes the leg of the ק kuf connected, he doesn't bother,
he won't bother, he'll just be like that,
right, that's easier.
So why is that is it suspended?
By the way, so the ק kuf has like a little tag,
so the ק kuf is reaching, the ק kadosh is reaching out
to the ר, reish, but the ר reish is facing away from
God or like they're not each other in the face, but he's
facing but he's reaching out. So why is the leg suspended off
of the roof? דאי הדר ביה ליעייל, de-i hadar bei layeil, because
if he wants to do תשובה, teshuvah, I'm making an opening for
him. If the רשע rasha wants to do תשובה teshuvah here, he
can just come straight back in like that. There's an opening. Okay,
it's open, the door's open, not closed. So the גמרא says וליעייל
בהך? u-layeil be-hach? Why not enter through the other way? The גמרא
says, you know, who needs to separate a door here? Let him
come up, there's an opening over there. He has to just get
around the leg of the ק. kuf. וליעייל בהך? u-layeil be-hach? So
it says מסייע ליה לריש לקיש, mesayei lei le-Reish Lakish, this supports
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, דאמר ריש לקיש, d'amar Reish Lakish, מאי דכתיב,
mai de-chtiv, what's meant by the verse, אם ללצים הוא יליץ, im
latsim hu yalits, if somebody wants to be like a mocker, he
will mock, ולענוים יתן חן, ve-la-anavim yiten chen, and to those that
are humble God will give kindness. So בא לטמא, ba letamei, if
somebody's trying to sin, פותחין לו, potchin lo, God won't step in,
won't prevent him, he'll open the door, he'll let him, you want
to sin? גזונטהייט, gezuntheit, God won't get in your way. But בא
לטהר, ba letaher, if you're coming to be pure, to purify yourself,
מסייעין אותו, mesayin oto, then God then God actually directly supports you.
So here it's true, the door was open, he could have gone
in this way, but God wants to help somebody who's coming to
do תשובה, teshuvah, so God actually opened up the door and actually
not just left the door open, but actually actively helped and therefore
gave another opening for the רשע rasha to come back.
So one minute, no. It says like this: ש Shin שקר, sheker,
ת, Tav, we're almost done, we got ש shin and ת. tav.
So ש shin is שקר, sheker, falsehood, ת tav אמת, emes, truth.
So it ends with, you know, it's interesting, all this stuff about
the righteous, about the ideal, and then in the end we're introducing
the רשע rasha and God and שקר sheker and truth, so to
tell you maybe the world isn't perfect, but God still provide, you
know, sort of welcomes the תשובה teshuvah and so on. So מאי
טעמא שקר מקרבן מיליה, mai ta'ama sheker mekarvin milei, אמת מרחקא מיליה?
emes merachaka milei? Why by שקר, sheker, the ש shin ק kuf
ר, reish, all those letters are near each other in the alphabet,
right? ר Reish ש shin ק, kuf, they're all near each other.
אמת Emes is completely equally spaced in the alphabet, א alef at
the beginning, מ mem in the middle, ת tav at the end.
So why is that? שיקרא שכיח, shikra shchiach, because שקר sheker is
very common, so there's a high density of שקר sheker in this
world. קושטא לא שכיח, kushta lo shchiach, truth is not so common,
so it's very spread out, okay, it's very hard to find truth.
ומאי טעמא שיקרא אחדא כרעיה קאי? u-mai ta'ama shikra achada krei kaei?
Why the word שקר, sheker, if you think about the ש shin
ק kuf and ר, reish, first of all the ש shin comes
to a point, the ר reish comes to a point, and the
ק kuf comes to a point, it's not a flat base—I mean,
depends how you write the ש—but shin not only that, the leg
of the ק, kuf, like, you know, שקר sheker stands on one
little leg, right?
Because if you have שקר, sheker, this is the base, it's all
standing on one little leg. אמת, Emes, every letter is flat and
standing on a very flat base.
Okay,
so ומאי טעמא שיקרא אחדא כרעיה קאי? u-mai ta'ama shikra achada krei
kaei? Why does שקר sheker stand on one leg, ואמת מלבן לבוניה,
ve-emes melaben libunei, and אמת emes is like bricks, it has a
very flat foundation. קושטא
קאי, kushta kaei, because in the end truth, you know, is established,
truth wins out or truth
establishes—sometimes sadly truth doesn't win out, but it means that the way
the מהרש״א Maharsha is explaining, truth creates, establishes the world, you know,
helps the world. שיקרא לא קאי, shikra lo kaei, שקר sheker either
doesn't survive, okay, although what's what's Mark Twain's line? He says, he
says what is it, like a lie can get halfway around the
world before truth has a chance to put its boots on or
something like that. Anyway, so all right, sometimes lies really do persist,
but... Okay, so now we thought through the whole אלף בית *Alef-Bet*.
Now we're not done. Now we're going to דרשן *darshen* also
letter combinations, a classic way that חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* would interpret words.
Sometimes they would do a letter substitution for certain גימטריה *gematria* or
for certain hidden codes, and the way they would do a letter
substitution, the most common one is אתב"ש *Atbash*. The way אתב"ש *Atbash*
works is,
I'll just write it this way: אלף *Alef*, בית *Bet*, גימל *Gimel*,
דלת *Dalet*, הית *Hey*, ויו *Vav*, זיין *Zayin*, חית Chet *Chet*, טית
*Tet*, יוד *Yod*, כף *Kaf*, 22 letters. Okay, so anyway, למד *Lamed*,
מם *Mem*,
נון *Nun*, סמך *Samekh*, עין *Ayin*, פא *Pei*, צדי *Tzadi*, קוף *Kof*,
ריש *Resh*, שין *Shin*, תיו *Tav*. See what I did here?
I folded it over. So that's a letter substitution. This is אתב"ש
*Atbash*: אלף תיו *Alef-Tav*, בית שין *Bet-Shin*, גימל ריש *Gimel-Resh*.
Okay, so now we're going to דרשן *darshen* the words that get
combined when you do that letter substitution. Okay, so
let's take a look. אתב"ש *Atbash*, אם אתה בוש *im ata bosh*,
אם אתה בוש *ata bosh*, if you are embarrassed, you're not brazen,
and you're embarrassed from sin, then גור דק *Gardak*. So אם אתה
עושה כן *im ata oseh ken*, if you do that, גור *gor*,
you will live. Did I skip a line?
Oh, okay, I'm sorry, where are we? Okay. אתב"ש *Atbash*. אותי תעב
*Ati te'ev*, if you despise me, את אבו לוא *et avo lo*.
So the אלף *alef* is אותי *oti*. If you despise me, God,
should I desire you? בית שין *Bet-Shin*, בי לא חשק *Bi lo
chashak*. So again, this is because we've introduced the idea of a
רשע *rasha*. So now we have to have a whole counterargument against
the רשע *rasha*. If somebody does not desire me, that's בית *bet*,
so שמי יחול עליו *shmi yachol alav*, will my name rest on
him? That's the שין *shin*. גימל ריש *Gimel-Resh*, גופו טמא *gufo timei*,
if somebody impurefied his body, ארחם עליו *aracham alav*? The ריש *resh*.
Should I have compassion on him? דק *Dak*, דלתותי נעל *daltosai na'al*.
He locked my doors, he didn't come into my house as it
were. קרניו לא אגדע *Karnav lo agade'a*? Should I not cut off
his horns? So עד כאן מדת רשעים *ad kan middas resha'im*. So
that's how to read the אתב"ש *Atbash* because we introduced a whole
רשע *rasha* at the end of the אלף בית *Alef-Bet* as a
response to the רשעים *resha'im*. אבל מדת צדיקים *Aval middas tzaddikim*, but
you could also read the אתב"ש *Atbash* because we also introduced צדיק
*tzaddik*, right? And אמת *emet*. So you could also read it to
talk to the צדיקים *tzaddikim*. אתב"ש *Atbash*, אם אתה בוש *im ata
bosh*, if you are embarrassed of sin, גור דק *gardak*. אם אתה
עושה כן *im ata oseh ken*, גור בדוק *gor bidok*. You will
live in the thin, the
supernal realms up in the heavens. הצו"ף *Hatzvaph*, הית צדי ויו פא
*hey-tzadi-vav-peh*. חציצה חץ חציצה *Chatziza hatz chatziza*. Okay. הוי בינך לאף *Havei
bincha l'af*. ויו *Vav* is like אף *af*. There should be a
wall between you and anger. זחסת"ן *Zachastan*. ואם אתה מזדעזע *Ve'im ata
mizdaze'a*, זיין *zayin*, if you tremble מן השטן *min hasatan*, חסתן *chastan*,
צדי קוף ריש שין תיו *tzadi, kof, resh, shin, tav*. חסתן *Chastan*,
השטן *Hasatan*. והחית *Chet* becomes a הית *hey*. If you tremble from
the שטן *satan*, you're afraid of sinning, then ים כל *yam kal*.
Then אמר שר של גיהנום *amar sar shel gehenom* לפני הקדוש ברוך
הוא *lifnei hakadosh baruch hu*. So then here's what will happen. The
angel of גיהנום *Gehenom* will say to God, ריבונו של עולם *Ribbono
shel olam*, master of the universe, לים כל *l'yam kol*. The ocean,
meaning גיהנום *Gehenom*, like the sea of fire whatever, let all come
in. He'll try to get everybody into גיהנום *Gehenom*. So אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא *amar hakadosh baruch hu*, so God says back to him,
so we just finished the אתב"ש *Atbash*, right? We did up to
ים כל *yam kal*.
Right, that's the end here, ים כל *yam kal*. And now we're
going to do another version of it, which is that we do
it after seven letters. אלף בית גימל דלת הית ויו זיין חית
Chet טית יוד כף למד מם נון *Alef, Bet, Gimel, Dalet, Hey,
Vav, Zayin, Chet, Tet, Yod, Kaf, Lamed, Mem,
Nun*. How did the חית Chet *het* get in there? I missed
the חית *het*. What did the חית *het* do? Let's go through
the triple. חס *Chas*. No, but אם אתה מזדעזע מן השטן חסתן
*im ata mizdaze'a min hasatan, chastan*... צדי קוף ריש שין
תיו *tzadi, kof, resh, shin, tav*.
חסתן *Chastan*, השטן *Hasatan*. Okay, so that's what we have now. We're
folding it over, we don't go backwards, we start again and we
do it every seven letters. 7 times 3 is 21, there are
22 letters so תיו *tav* is extra. Okay, so here we have.
So אחס בטג"ף *achas batagif*. See אחס בטג"ף *achas batagif*? Those three
words there. אני חס עליהם *ani chas aleihem*. So God says, no,
you want to get everybody into גיהנום *Gehenom*, אלף *alef* אני חס
*ani chas*. I will have compassion on them. מפני שבעטו *mipnei shebi'atu*,
בית טית *bet-tet*, בעטו *bo'etu*. They kicked away. בגי"ף *bagif*. בגי"ף *Bagif*
is רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it's sort of like זיוף *zi'uf* or
ניאוף *ni'uf*. It sounds like adultery, which is a common I guess
a profound יצר הרע *yetzer hara*. So no, I'm going to have
compassion on them. דח"ץ *Dachatz*, דכינים הם *dachinim hem*, כנים הם *kenim
hem*, צדיקים הם *tzaddikim hem*. So דלת כף צדי *dalet-kaf-tzadi*. They are
lowly, they are righteous, they are upright, they are righteous, הם *hem*.
הלק *Halak*. הית למד קוף *hey-lamed-kuf*. We're almost done there. אין לך
חלק בהם *ein lecha chelek bahem*. הלק חלק *Halak-chelek*. הית *Hey* and
חית *het* we're playing around with a lot. You have no portion
in them. גיהנום *Gehenom* doesn't get any of these צדיקים *tzaddikim*. ומרזן
ש"ת *Umarzan shat*. That's the last two, ומרזן ש"ת *umarzan shat*. Right,
those are the last two columns. אמר גיהנום לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא
*amar Gehenom lifnei hakadosh baruch hu*. So גיהנום *Gehenom* says to God,
ריבונו *ribbono*... רבונו של עולם מרי (*Ribono shel Olam Mari*) my master
מר זניני (*Mar zaneni*) you have to feed me I'm hungry I
need the souls of people okay so and מזרעו של שת (*mizaro
shel Shet*) and give me from the שין תו (*Shin Tav*) from
the seed of שת (*Shet*) the Jewish people I mean שת (*Shet*)
is more than the Jewish people but it includes the Jewish people
אמר ליה (*Amar leh*) so God says and now we're going to
do another one which is which is similar to the את בש
(*At Bash*) except instead of folding over we do it like we
did this we start we do it like this ל מ mem
נ ס ע פ צ ק ר ש ת (*Lamed Mem Nun
Samech Ayin Pey Tzadik Kof Reish Shin Tav*) you got it like
this instead of folding over okay so now we're going to make
the דרשה (*drasha*) אל בם גן דת (*Al Bam Gan Das*) okay
so so he says אמר ליה אל בם גן דת להיכן אוליכם
א-ל (*Amar leh Al Bam Gan
Das leichan oliceim A-E-L*) where will I bring them בם
(*Bam*) where will I bring them גן דת לגן הדס (*Gan Das
le Gan Hadas*) to the Garden of Myrtle meaning גן עדן (*Gan
Eden*) no no no you're not getting בני ישראל (*Bnei Yisrael*) I'm
bringing them to גן עדן (*Gan Eden*) ה Heh, ו ף (*Havaf*)
so אמר גהנום לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא רבונו של עולם עייף אנכי
(*Amar Gehenom lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu Ribono shel Olam ayef anochi*) ה
ו ף (*Havaf*) I don't know עייפא (*ayefa*) or something so I
am weary you know I need sustenance ז צ ח ק (*Zatzchak*)
הללו (*halalu*) so God says no sorry הללו זרעו זיין צדיק חת
קוף ז צ ח ק (*halalu zaro zayin tzadik chet kof Zatzchak*)
הזרעו של יצחק (*hazaro shel Yitzchak*) they are the seed of יצחק
(*Yitzchak*) you don't get them so ט ר י ש ק ת
(*Tar Yashkat*) which is the end טר יש לי (*Tar yesh li*)
so I watch for me like נטר (*Natar*) is observe נטר (*Natar*)
in Aramaic יש לי כתות כתות יש קת (*yesh li kitot kitot
yesh kat*) I have many many groups שעובדי כוכבים שאני נותן לך
(*she'oveidi kochavim she'ani noten lach*) don't worry I'll give you the non-Jews
okay so we made a whole דרשה (*drasha*) from the אלף בית
(*Aleph Beis*) to the את בש (*At Bash*) to the אחס (*Achas*)
to the אל (*Al*) all about all about the how you're supposed
to act in the world the צדיקים (*tzadikim*) the רשעים (*reshaim*) and
that God opens up a פתח (*petach*) for the רשעים (*reshaim*) but
the צדיקים (*tzadikim*) get their reward and the רשעים (*reshaim*) get their
just deserts so it's actually interesting like what is the point of
this on the one
hand it's a very nice way of teaching
מוסר (*mussar*) like
it's a good vehicle to communicate these messages and it
really is great that you can do these types of plays with
the letters but one also wonders if it's also some type of
a message of some type of a mystical power in the Hebrew
alphabet and in the order of the Hebrew אלף בית (*aleph beis*)
the fact that you're able to do this reinforces this idea of
the mystical power of the letters and the organization of the letters
which could go back to what the מהרש''א (*Maharsha*) was trying to
say what's the point about why the לוחות (*luchos*) were read backwards
to tell you that there's all these ways of combining it and
so on so that is obviously and that had a very profound
implication
in קבלה (*Kabbalah*) and mystical type of activities the power of the
of the Hebrew alphabet and of the letters yes
isn't that why it was presented as young students coming to the
בית מדרש (*beis medrash*) introducing this that they're looking into the future
to the
קבלה (*Kabbalah*) maybe or like somehow sense like that they have they
somehow cut to the truth beyond all of this intellectual activity that
we're doing maybe I was going to mention something about יהושע בן
נון (*Yehoshua bin Nun*) what the מהרש''א (*Maharsha*) says why יהושע בן
נון (*Yehoshua bin Nun*) so he says well because part of this
דרשה (*drasha*) incorporated the מ סופית (*mem sofit*) and the נ סופית
(*nun sofit*) and the מ (*mem*) open and closed and we said
that that was forgotten and that it had to be re-established so
since it was forgotten for such a long time the last time
they were able to do this דרשה (*drasha*) was at the time
of יהושע בן נון (*Yehoshua bin Nun*) before it had been forgotten
I'm not exactly sure about that I think it's interesting that the
נון (*nun*) when it was written here in the גמרא (*Gemara*) and
I don't know in the original manuscripts is written with a tzip
tzip it's נון ו נון (*nun vav nun*) because נון (*nun*) is
also one of the letters is a נון (*nun*) so I'm wondering
if that also was why they picked יהושע בן נון (*Yehoshua bin
Nun*) because we're playing with letters and his word one of his
name is the letter is the letter נון (*nun*)
yeah all of them are standing back to back as well with
the ק ר (*Kuf Reish*) that the ק (*Kuf*) is turning away
from the ר (*Resh*) and the
ר (*Resh*) is turning away no I know I know רש''י (*Rashi*)
says that we said it the other way out of respect for
God we don't want the רשע (*Rasha*) is turning away from God
we want to say God's turning away from the רשע (*Rasha*)
one other thing I mean is the next thing is a משנה
Mishnah, (*Mishnah*) what about
like what we פוסקין (*Paskin*) like can you tell me no okay
so turning the page we now continue with the issues of כתיבה
ksiva, (*Kesiva*) so after that very lovely דרשה (*drasha*) so it says
like this הכותב שתי אותיות (*Hakosev shtei osiyos*) someone who writes two
letters we've even saying that two letters is the מלאכה (*melacha*) בהעלם
אחד Echad (*b'helem echad*) in one state of forgetfulness חייב chayav, (*chayav*)
you're חייב chayav. (*chayav*) that's pretty much what we said before anyways
so recapping it כותב בדיו (*cosev b'dyo*) or what qualify it in
a minute at the end of the משנה Mishnah (*mishnah*) כותב בדיו
(*cosev b'dyo*) if somebody wrote in ink or בסם בסיקרא בקומוס ובקנקנתום
(*bisam bisikra b'kumos b'kankantom*) or all different other types of permanent mark
permanent inks that are things that make permanent marks the גמרא (*Gemara*)
will identify what these are ובכל דבר שהוא רושם u-ve-khol davar she-hu
roshem (*uv'chol davar shehu roshem*) anything that makes a mark and actually
means a permanent mark חייב chayav, (*chayav*) it doesn't matter not only
ink okay same it's not only Hebrew it's not like just the
writing of a ספר תורה (*Sefer Torah*) now שתי (*Shtei*) זוויות, if
you write on two walls and they're at a
corner, ועל שני לוחי פנקס, ve-al shenei lukhei pinkas, or on two
sort of sections of a, of a sorry, on two sections
of a ledger, so then are you חייב chayav or not? If
one letter's on each wall or one letter is on each section?
So it says
והן נהגין זה עם זה, ve-hen ne-hagin ze im ze, if they're
read one with the other, they like lead one into the other,
חייב. chayav So basically, if you write at the corner of a
wall, when you write an א aleph at that corner and a
ב, you know, right next to it at the next corner, so
you can read them around the curve like that as one word,
just one word on a bent surface, you're חייב. Similarly, if you
write it on two sections of a ledger and you write an
א aleph here or ב here, you know, so that they're read,
even though they're on different sections, when you read them, you read
them continuously as one word. Okay, but if you write one letter
on that wall and one letter on that wall, so even though
you wrote two letters, you did not write a two-letter word and
you are פטור. patur. Okay, so it says הכותב
על בשרו, ha-kotev al besaro, if you write on your flesh, חייב,
presumably with ink or something, you're חייב. Again, that raises a question
about permanence, but you know, the thing is that it will last
for a while until you wash it off. Permanent does not mean,
like I said, you know, if you write with a pencil, it's
not like oh, it's אינו מתקיים eino mitkayem because you can erase
it. מתקיים mitkayem does not merely definition, אינו מתקיים eino mitkayem doesn't
mean it's able to be reversed. It means that it naturally has
no permanence. So the question is how long? I mean, things written
on your skin even if you don't bathe, normally just by rubbing,
I mean, I guess it depends on the type of ink, but
it will still last for a little while. So how permanent is
permanent is an important question.
They make many days edible ink for kids.
That we're not talking about that yet. Yes.
I heard there's an idea of not writing on yourself. Is that
like, is that something?
Oh, you mean because of like a tattoo issue?
No, no, just in general I thought. People write, kids always write
on themselves. Never heard it?
Nope. You'd be interested to track that down. Haven't heard of that.
Okay, so the גמרא says so המשרט על בשרו, ha-mesaret al besaro,
let's say you scratch in your flesh, right? You scratch something in,
so it's not like deep enough with ink, you're not making a
tattoo, but you're scratching something and you know, you can still see
those scratches for a little while. So in that case רבי אליעזר
מחייב Rabbi Eliezer mechayev and וחכמים פוטרים. va-Chachamim potrim. Chachamim say you're
פטור. patur. Why? Either because it's not permanent, because maybe the scratches
will naturally undo faster, or maybe more likely that they define writing
as the use, as the applying of some type of an ink,
you know, onto paper with an instrument as opposed to etching. That's
not the same as writing. Now of course you have to ask
at what stage? You mean if I take a chisel and I
carve something into stone, that's not writing? So presumably it is. Right.
So presumably I don't mean ink. I can write without ink. If
I carve, so it's not unclear what the issue here is. Maybe
it's, we'll see in the גמרא, it more has to do with
like a שינוי. shinuy. It's not the דרך. derech. Not because it's
ink, not because it's not permanent, maybe it's permanent enough the same
way ink on your skin is, but it's just not a normal
way of writing something is writing it with, you know, scratching it
on your skin.
And then you have a חבלה chavala issue?
It's even though you didn't do חבלה, chavala, it's only a scratch.
Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Now הכותב על בשרו, ha-kotev
al besaro, and we just did that. How we just did that.
וחכמים פוטרים. va-Chachamim potrim. כותב במשקין, kotev be-mashkin, if you wrote in
liquids, במי פירות be-mei peirot or fruit juice, meaning now we're talking
about non-permanent, and this is important because this is the first משנה
that really emphasizes impermanence as an exemption. We mentioned before אינו מתקיים,
eino mitkayem, but there it was more like incomplete. Here it's really
about impermanence. So if you wrote in liquids or in fruit juices,
באבק דרכים be-avak drakhim in dust, you know, you you know like
it could mean you wrote into the dust like, you know, like
somebody writes on a car, "wash me," or something like that. Although
some cars that aren't being washed, it's pretty permanent anyway. Or you
use dust to make the marks, באבק הסופרים be-avak ha-sofrim or like
the sort of the you know the leftover dust from the scribes
like a type of a black substance but apparently it wouldn't be
so permanent. ובכל דבר שאינו מתקיים, u-ve-khol davar she-eino mitkayem, anything that
is not, doesn't last, פטור. patur. So here אינו מתקיים eino mitkayem
means impermanent. לאחר ידו, le-akhar yado, if you wrote with the back
of your hand, not you know, you held the pen upside down
as it were, so you were moving you know rather than holding
the front of your hand it was in the back of your
hand.
Does it mean that you use the back of your hand to
write?
No. ברגלו, be-raglo, or you did it with your foot, בפיו, be-piv,
if your mouth you held your pen, ובמרפקו, u-ve-marpeko, your underarm or
your or your elbow, כותב אותו, kotev oto, all those are a
שינוי, shinuy, similar to when we talked about carrying in an unusual
way. כתב אות אחת סמוך לכתב. katav ot achat samukh li-khtav. Now
let's say you didn't write two letters, but you wrote one letter
next to a word. So you had a word which was I
don't know ש-נ-י shin-nun-yud and you came and you wrote a מ
and turned it into שנים. shnayim. Okay, so you actually made a
whole word there, but you only wrote one letter.
So וכתב על גבי כתב, ve-katav al gabei ktav, or if you
wrote on top, you had a word written. and then you re-inked
it. I mean, it was readable beforehand but you added a layer
of ink. נתכוון לכתוב חית וכתב שני זיינין, Niskavein likhtov chet ve-khasav
shenei zayinin, you wanted to write a חית and instead you wrote
two זיינין Zayinin because very often a חית in the ספר תורה
is written sort of like a, I mean, I'm not doing this
fancy, but it's sort of written like, you know,
two זיינין Zayinin with like a, like a hat on it.
So you wanted to write a חית and you didn't do the
hat and it became
two
זיינין. Zayinin. אחת בארץ ואחת בקורה Achas ba-aretz ve-achas ba-kora or now
this is contrasting the earlier cases in the משנה, you wrote one
letter on the ground and one on the beam, you know, you
wrote two letters but they didn't, they can't be read together, or
כותב על שני כותלי הבית, Kosev al shenei koslei ha-bayis, or you
wrote on two walls but they're not at the corner, at two
opposite walls, על שני דפי פנקס ואין נהגין זה עם זה Al
shenei dappe pinkas ve-ein nehagin zeh im zeh or on two sections
of the ledger but they are different sections and you can't, the
letters don't read together, פטור. Patur. So in all those cases you
even you wrote one letter and not two, even though one letter
added to a word, or you wrote two letters but they don't
read together, in those cases you are exempt. כותב אות אחת נוטריקון,
Kosev os achas nutrikon, let's say you write one letter, this somebody
asked us the other day I think, let's say you write one
letter which symbolizes a whole word. Meaning you wrote like, I don't
know, let's say like this, let's say you wrote א Aleph with
a line which everybody understood meant like אלהים Elokim or something like
that, or אחד or something of that nature. Okay, so you only
wrote one letter but it represents a whole word. So there רבי
יהושע בן בתירא מחייב, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Betira mechayeiv, רבי יהושע בן
בתירא Rabbi Yehoshua ben Betira says you're חייב, you basically wrote something
that represents a whole word and maybe more than adding a letter
to a word because that only meant something in combination of the
word that already existed. Here your whole one letter represented an entire
word even though it wasn't two letters. וחכמים פוטרין ve-Chachamim potrin and
וחכמים ve-Chachamim say even there you're פטור, patur, there's a minimum of
two letters even if your one letter is able to represent something.
It also, by the way, if you go back to the opinion
in the previous משנה that it's not about writing, כתיבה, but it's
about, it's about רושם, roshem, making the meaningful mark, then certainly you
would understand that these types of things might not be limited to
two letters, you know, anytime that those marks become meaningful. Yes, Charlie?
So all these things that you've described as פטור, patur, they would
be רבנן. Rabanan.
Oh yeah, they're all just biblical exemptions, רבנן Rabanan it's certainly all
אסור. assur.
But isn't it a matter of writing a whole word then the
חכמים Chachamim should agree that if you write a ה, you should
be חייב because that's the letter השם Hashem symbolizes, and blah blah
blah blah.
No, no, that's a prefix, that's a prefix, no, I mean that's
no, in standard Hebrew you don't have one letter words. Okay, now
somebody asked the other day, what about if you wrote in English
a one letter word? Right? I or A. Are the rabbis always
saying that two is a, right, I or A. Are the rabbis
always saying that two is a minimum, or are they saying two
is a minimum in Hebrew where you can't, you don't have a
full word without two letters? That's not clear.
And marks like a check?
Right, so that would be like רושם, roshem, that would be the
opinion that said, that said that there's a חיוב chiyuv for marking,
a significant symbol even if it's not a letter. Okay, but that
was a debate of תנאים Tannaim before about that. All right, so
now you're going to ask Michael's question, how do we פוסק? posken?
All right, let's take a look at the גמרא. דיו, Dyo, what's
דיו? dyo? דיותא, Diyuta, which is I don't know, which is your
standard ink. סם Sam is סמא, Sama, I don't know, it's some
other marking thing, I know your ArtScrolls and Jastrow and whatever, סנצינו
Soncino probably tells you, not סנצינו, Soncino, whatever, שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz probably tells
you what it is, I think he said, I think I checked
that שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz said סם sam was some type of a yellow
pigment. סיקרא, Sikra, so אמר רבה בר בר חנה Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chanah סיקרתא, sikrasa, some type of a red mark, a red
pigment, שמע. shema. קומוס, Komus, what's קומוס? komus? קומא. Koma. All right,
so some other type of a gum-based type of a, of a
pigment. קנקנתום, Kankanatum, what's קנקנתום? kankanatum? אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
שמואל Amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah amar Shmuel חרתא דאושכפי. chartah d'ushkafi.
It's some type of a black used by shoemakers, again another type
of a pigment. Okay, ובכל דבר שהוא רושם לאתויי מאי, l'atuyei mai,
what does that include? לאתויי הא דתני רבי חנינא l'atuyei ha d'tani
Rabbi Chanina כתבו במי טבריא, kesavo bi-mei Tverya, this is talking about
writing a גט. get. But a גט get also has to be
written in permanent ink. So what if it's good for a גט,
get, if it's considered permanent, it would be good for שבת. So
if you wrote, I'm sorry, I wrote, I said that wrong. כתבו
במי טרייא, kesavo bi-mei Tarya, if you wrote with waters of טרייא,
Tarya, which רש"י says is some type of a fruit or some
type of a thing that actually makes a permanent stain, maybe it's
like blueberry juice or
something or pomegranate, yeah, really stains.
ואפצא, ve-aftsa, אפצא aftsa is another type of like a black pigment,
כשר. תני רבי חייא Tani Rabbi Chiya כתבו באבק, kesavo b'avak, if
you wrote in dust, again, we mentioned אבק דרכים avak derakhim you're
פטור, patur, so it must be a, another type of a dust
that leaves a permanent mark. בשחור בשיחור, bi-shchor bi-shichor, different types of
black types of pigments, כשר. Again, a גט get is כשר, which
means it's permanent, which means you're חייב for שבת. Okay, המשרט על
בשרו, ha-mesaret al besaro, if you scratch on the skin. המשרט על
בשרו hamisaret al besaro if you scratch into your flesh. תניא tanya
אמר להן רבי אליעזר לחכמים, amar lahen Rabbi Eliezer lachachamim, Rabbi Eliezer
said to the חכמים, chachamim, how can you say that scratching into
your flesh is not a normal way of writing? ולא בן סטדא
velo Ben Stada didn't Ben Stada הוציא כשפים ממצרים בשריטה? hotzi kshafim
miMitzrayim bisrita? He smuggled out, we'll talk about this, he smuggled out,
you know, special incantations and witchcrafts out of Egypt by writing it
into his flesh. Somehow they wouldn't, so he wouldn't be caught. It
was a way of smuggling it out. על בשרו al besaro by
scratching it into his flesh. אמרו לו amru lo שוטה היה, shoteh
haya, he was an idiot. They מביאין ראיה מן השוטים. ein mevi'in
ra'aya min hashotim. You don't bring proof from some of these? Anyway,
what does that mean? So Rashi adds it doesn't mean he's an
idiot like he didn't have intelligence, it means that he was so
משוגע meshuga to want to get out this witchcraft, he was willing
to do anything. So he wrote it in this way, which is
not the way any normal person writes, but he was so passionate
about finding a way to get it out, he was willing to
write in this crazy way. Now our גמרא ends here. However, there
is an interesting
censored few next lines of the גמרא with... Steinsaltz did put it
in. Yeah, so can you, you can hand me here. Here's a
Steinsaltz. No, that's the wrong one.
Steinsaltz did put it in. I was trying to find other editions
that didn't. So here it is in Steinsaltz. It says בן סטדא,
Ben Stada, you're telling me his name was בן סטדא? Ben Stada?
בן פנדירא הוא. Ben Pandira hu. We know his name was בן
פנדירא. Ben Pandira. So אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, בעל סטדא.
ba'al Stada.
No, his his mother's father's name was סטדא, Stada, so he's called
בן סטדא. Ben Stada. בועל, bo'el, but the one his mother really
had sex with, his real father, his biological father, was פנדירא. Pandira.
So therefore he had two names, בן סטדא Ben Stada and בן
פנדירא. Ben Pandira. His biological father and the father who raised him.
So אמר רב
חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, I'm sorry, I just did that. בעל, ba'al,
so the גמרא says one minute, בעל ba'al was פפוס בן יהודה
הוא. Pappos ben Yehuda hu. No, the mother's father wasn't this סטדא,
Stada, it was פפוס בן יהודה. Pappos ben Yehuda. So why is
he called בן סטדא? Ben Stada? אלא אמו סטדא, ela imo Stada,
fine. His mother was סטדא. Stada. So therefore and his, you know,
his biological father was פנדירא. Pandira. So that's how he's בן סטדא
Ben Stada and he's בן פנדירא, Ben Pandira, and his father was
someone else. So the גמרא says his mother was סטדא. Stada. אמו,
imo, his mother, מרים מגדלא שיער נשייא הויא. Miryam megadla sa'ar nashaya
hava. She was מרים Miryam who braided the hair of women.
אלא, כדאמרי בפומבדיתא, kid'amri b'Pumbedita, what does it mean סטדא? Stada? סטת
דא מבעלה. stat da miba'alah. It means that she סט, sat, she,
she strayed from her husband, she committed adultery because her the biological
father was was this פנדירא Pandira guy. Now what is this talking
about? It seems like they're clearly talking about some figure they know
about and why was it censored? So you see so
many people believe that at least the belief was that this was
referring to Jesus. And some people want to even go further and
say first of all מרים מגדלא שיער נשייא Miryam megadla sa'ar nashaya
sounds like Mary Magdalene although that might have been if that's true
that that's what they thought then it was confusing, you know,
Mary Magdalene with the Virgin Mary because Mary Magdalene was one of
Jesus' disciples, was not the mother. Okay if that's what they thought.
What's this סטדא Stada and פנדירא Pandira and so on? Well first
of all a point being made is is is is that his
mother committed adultery. You know so yeah, virgin birth, I've heard that
one before, right? So how did she really get pregnant? Oh well
this is why, this is how she got pregnant, you know, with
somebody else. So that's, you know, if that if that's what's going
on here like and then some even go further and make the
argument that פנדירא Pandira is a play on the Greek word for
virgin. Because the Greek word for virgin is I looked this up
before and I mean I I've heard this many years ago, parthenos
or something like that. Anyway there's a Greek word for virgin that
sounds very, that's very much like this. Anyway that is a here,
I'll tell you what the Greek word is. The Greek word is
parthenos is virgin in Greek. So I guess... Okay so anyway but
other scholars basically this was first put out about a hundred and
twenty years ago by somebody but I I was just redoing some
reading on it and some people claim like this you know really
like believe it's total שקר sheker I mean you know scholars, not
whatever, think that it's it's not at all what the גמרא is
talking about and actually that that maybe it was actually anti-Semitic, the
desire to try to identify this as a mocking of Jesus maybe,
but anyway that is a real question, what is going on with
this גמרא. One of the reasons to say it's not Jesus is
that the time doesn't work out because this פפוס בן יהודה Pappos
ben Yehuda or whatever, you know, in the other places where בן
סטדא Ben Stada are mentioned, if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafot, בן סטדא Ben Stada אומר רבנו תם דהא בן סטדא דאמרינן
הכא הוא דהוה בימי פפוס בן יהודה דהוה בימי רבי עקיבא. omer
Rabbeinu Tam deha Ben Stada de'amrinan hacha hu dehava bimei Pappos ben
Yehuda dehava bimei Rabbi Akiva. So that that the
the fact that it identifies it with with פפוס בן יהודה Pappos
ben Yehuda is the time of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is the
wrong generation. Again it doesn't mean that חז"ל didn't conflate different things,
you know, and they, you know, how accurate did they have the
exact chronology of these things is not clear. But it is a
very fascinating גמרא that has been interpreted in that way. But they
say הוציא כשפים ממצרים.
hotzi kshafim miMitzrayim. What? They say הוציא כשפים ממצרים. hotzi kshafim miMitzrayim.
If it was Jesus he wasn't in מצרים. Mitzrayim.
Yeah well you mean if it meant at the time of the
Exodus. Yeah. But if we're talking about רבי עקיבא... Rabbi Akiva... What?
Didn't they say he took כשפים kishufim out of מצרים? Mitzrayim? What?
Didn't they say he took כשפים kishufim out of מצרים? Mitzrayim? If
it was Jesus, he was in מצרים. Mitzrayim. Yeah, well, you mean
if it meant at the time of the Exodus? But if we're
talking about רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's also, doesn't mean at the time
of the Exodus. But that, but right, but thank you for mentioning
it, the desire of identifying with כשפים kishufim is also probably if
it is about Jesus, an attempt to try to explain where did
we get all these miracle stories of Jesus, how was he able
to do this, unless we say it was all false. Oh, he
was able to do it because he smuggled these witchcrafts out of
מצרים. Mitzrayim. So that if you understand that this is and even
if the פנתירא פנדרא Panteros Pandera is not meant as this pun
on this word virgin, it does seem like it could very much
be this type of a, this hidden type of a what do
you call polemic about Jesus and his mother and so on. Anyway,
so we will end with that, we will pick up tomorrow with
more things about writing. Okay?
At some point get שטיינזלץ'ס Steinsaltz's point? שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz points out that
in the
other uncensored manuscripts of the תלמוד, Talmud, when they talk about Jesus,
they actually remember that.